Guide to the Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc. records, 1923-1999 UA.01.08.0004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc. records
1923-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc
UA.01.08.0004
14 Linear Feet
The Angier B. Duke Memorial was established in 1925 by Benjamin N. Duke to honor his son, Angier Buchanan Duke (1884-1923, Trinity, '05). The program was reworked in 1946-1947 when the Memorial Scholarship became the University's premier undergraduate award. The collection contains annual reports of various committees, correspondence and memoranda, studies, proposals, financial material, and miscellaneous material. A majority of the material pertains to loans, awards, and scholarships funded by the Angier B. Duke Memorial and ranges in date from 1923-1999.
approx. 9500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc. records were received by the University Archives as a transfer between 1973-1986.
Historical Note
The Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc. was established in 1925 by Ben N. Duke to honor his son, Angier Buchanan Duke (1884-1923). The Memorial is a nonprofit membership corporation organized to develop scholarship and to promote and further the arts, sciences, and professions by establishing funding to assist students. Prior to the Second World War the Memorial focused primarily on assisting struggling students through the years of the Great Depression. In May 1946, several members of the Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc. Board of Directors expressed concern over existing policy governing scholarship awards. These concerned members felt that student financial aid would take on new significance in the future when G.I Bill funding began to wane. The board formed a committee in 1946 to explore possible directions a new financial aid policy could take.
The new Scholarship Program shifted from need-based determination to considerations of academic merit and future professional potential. The Program "sought to attract young men and young women with the character, personality, intellectual integrity, vitality, and imagination to become leaders in their chosen fields" who could "digest and use the knowledge they acquired." The result, the Angier B. Duke Memorial Scholarship, became the premiere undergraduate award at Duke. In 1974, the Memorial initiated three new facets of the scholarship program: Summer Study at Oxford Program, the Self-Determined Educational Experience Program, and the Angier B. Duke In-Class Scholar Award.
Collection Overview
The collection contains material pertaining to the operation of the Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc. scholarship, award, and loan programs. The material ranges in date from 1923-1999. General files include material relating to all of the scholarship programs offered by the Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc.: Summer Study at Oxford, Self-Determined Educational Experience, In-Class Scholar Award, and the Angier B. Duke Memorial Scholarship; reports, correspondence, and miscellaneous material. The restricted series contains bound annual reports of the scholarship and prize committees, a sampling of student loan applications, and annual Memorial Scholar student essays. Financial papers include loan amounts and balances, assorted vouchers, corporate investment material, and several oversize items: bound ledgers, cash books, and journals.
Related Material
Scholarships Reference Collection, 1953-ongoing
Duke University Archives
The Benjamin Newton Duke papers, 1834-1984, bulk, 1884-1929
Duke University Archives
Awards Reference Collection, 1879-ongoing
Duke University Archives
Angier B. Duke Memorial Scholarship; Duke, Angier B., 1884-1923; Durham, Plato Tracy, 1873-1930; Duke University -- Funds and scholarships; Duke University. Angier B. Duke Scholarship Committee -- Periodicals; Duke, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Newton); Duke University. Angier B. Duke Scholarship Committee; Duke University. Trinity College of Arts and Sciences -- Funds and scholarships; Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc. -- Periodicals; Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc; Angier B. Duke Memorial, Inc; Duke University -- Endowments -- Periodicals
- General Files, 1923-1999, 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Various administrative files including proposals, awards, scholarships, programs, and projects material, correspondence and memoranda, reports, and miscellaneous material.
  - Propsal for Oxford Program and revising Angier B. Duke Program, 1973, undated (Box 1)
  - Report on Oxford Program and Self-Determined Educational Experience (SDEE), 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - SDEE guidelines, undated (Box 1)
  - SDEE Project, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - SDEE Project, 1975 (Box 1)
  - SDEE Project, 1976 (Box 1)
  - SDEE Project, 1977 (Box 1)
  - E.W. Wittig, SDEE Project, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Scholarship Advisor duties, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report, R. Fred Zuker, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Report of the Undergraduate Faculty Committee on Arts and Sciences/Admissions and Financial Aid, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Financial Aid, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Advisor's Summary Report, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Ernestein Friedl request, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Dean John M. Fein's report, 1978 (Box 1)
  - "A Study of the Angier B. Duke Scholarship," undated (Box 1)
  - "A Final Study of the A.B. Duke Memorial Scholarship," 1975 (Box 1)
  - In-Class Scholarships, 1974 (Box 1)
  - In-Class Scholarships, 1975 (Box 1)
  - In-Class Scholarships, 1976 (Box 1)
  - In-Class Scholarships, 1977 (Box 1)
  - In-Class Scholarships, 1978 (Box 1)
  - In-Class Scholarships, 1979 (Box 1)
  - In-Class Scholarships, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Angier B. Duke Program, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous records, 1946-1966 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous records, 1966-1975 (Box 3)
  - Summary of loans and payments, 1926-1949 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1951, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1973, 1975, 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1980, 1986, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1991-1992, 1995, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Biennial Reports, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - "Ave Atque Vale, Frater!," by Plato Tracy Durham (dedicated to Angier B. Duke), 1923 (Box 3)
  - Address, "Origins and Early Development of the Angier B. Duke Memorial Scholarship Program," by Alan K. Manchester (Box 3)
  - M.A. Thesis, "An Evolution of the Procedures Used in Selecting Angier B. Duke Memorial Scholars, 1947-1958," 1964 (Box 3)
  - M.A. Thesis, "A Comparison of the Academic Achievement of Siblings in the Angier B. Duke Program at Duke University," 1958 (Box 3)
  - Angier B. Duke Memorial-meeting minutes (bound), 2004-2007 (Box 16)
- Restricted Material, 1925-1976, 5 boxes
  Bound reports of various prize, award, and scholarship committees, a sampling of student loan applications, and Memorial Scholar annual essays.
  - Loan Applications, 1925-1929 (Box 4)
  - Loan Applications, 1930-1939 (Box 4)
  - Loan Applications, 1940-1949 (Box 4)
  - Loan Applications, 1950-1959 (Box 4)
  - Loan Applications, 1960-1967 (Box 4)
  - Report of the Angier B. Duke (ABD) Regional Scholarship Committee, 1948-1949 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Regional Prizes Committee, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Regional Prizes Committee, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Regional Prizes Committee, 1951-1952 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Regional Prizes Committee, 1951-1952 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Regional Prizes Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Regional Prizes Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Regional Prizes Committee, 1953-1954 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Regional Prizes Committee, 1953-1954 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Regional Prizes Committee, 1954-1955 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Prize Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Prize Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Prize Committee, 1956-1957 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Prize Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Prize Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Prize Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Prize Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1962-1963 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1962-1963 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 8)
  - Report of the ABD Memorial Scholarship Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 8)
  - Memorial Scholars Annual Essays, 1962 (Box 8)
  - Memorial Scholars Annual Essays, 1962 (Box 8)
- Financial Papers, 1925-1961, 7 boxes
  Loan amounts and balances, assorted vouchers, corporate investment material, and several oversize items: bound ledgers, cash books, and journals.
  - Form letter "A" to delinquent borrowers, 1948-1950 (Box 9)
  - Form letter "A" and "B" to delinquent borrowers, 1950 (Box 9)
  - Letters to delinquent borrowers, 1950 (Box 9)
  - Student loan reports, 1940-1944 (Box 9)
  - Student loan trial balances, 1945-1947 (Box 9)
  - Student loan trial balances, 1948-1950 (Box 9)
  - Student loan trial balances, 1951-1953 (Box 9)
  - Student loan trial balances, 1954-1956 (Box 9)
  - Student loan trial balances, 1957-1958 (Box 9)
  - Student loan trial balances, 1959-1960 (Box 9)
  - Corporation Trust Company, 1925-1958 (Box 9)
  - Investments, 1942-1951 (Box 9)
  - Investments, Florida property, 1939-1942 (Box 9)
  - Vouchers, 1925-1933 (Box 9)
  - Vouchers, 1934-1936 (Box 9)
  - Vouchers, 1936-1938 (Box 9)
  - Vouchers, 1939-1941 (Box 9)
  - Vouchers, 1939-1944 (Box 9)
  - Vouchers, 1945-1947 (Box 9)
  - Vouchers, 1947-1950 (Box 10)
  - Vouchers, 1951-1953 (Box 10)
  - Vouchers, 1954-1957 (Box 10)
  - Cash Book No. 1, 1925-1931 (Box 10)
  - Cash Book No. 2, 1931-1941 (Box 10)
  - Cash Book No. 3, 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Journal No. 1, 1925-1942 (Box 10)
  - Ledger No. 1, 1925-1942 (Box 10)
  - Cash Book No. 4, 1942-1954 (Box 11, Oversize)
  - Cash Book/Journal folio sheets, 1954-1961 (Box 12, Oversize)
  - Medical Student Study and payment record ratings, 1932-1947 (Box 13, Oversize)
  - Group statements, 1925-1946 (Box 14, Oversize)
  - Journal No. 2, 1942-1954 (Box 15, Oversize)